<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2014) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2014) -->

<section anchor="xdr_desc" title="XDR Description of the Flexible File Layout Type">
  <t>
    This document contains the external data representation (XDR)
    <xref target='RFC4506' /> description of the flexible file
    layout type version 2.  The XDR description is embedded in this
    document in a way that makes it simple for the reader to extract
    into a ready-to-compile form.  The reader can feed this document
    into the following shell script to produce the machine readable
    XDR description of the flexible file layout type version 2:
  </t>

  <t>
    &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
#!/bin/sh
grep '^ *///' $* | sed 's?^ */// ??' | sed 's?^ *///$??'
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
  </t>

  <t>
    That is, if the above script is stored in a file called "extract.sh", and
    this document is in a file called "spec.txt", then the reader can do:
  </t>

  <figure>
    <artwork>
sh extract.sh &lt; spec.txt &gt; flex_filesv2_prot.x
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    The effect of the script is to remove leading white space from each
    line, plus a sentinel sequence of "///".
  </t>

  <t>
    The embedded XDR file header follows.
    Subsequent XDR descriptions, with the sentinel sequence are
    embedded throughout the document.
  </t>

  <t>
    Note that the XDR code contained in this document depends on
    types from both the flex files version 1 flex_filesv2_prot.x
    file (<xref target='flexfiles' />) and the NFSv4.1 nfs4_prot.x
    file (<xref target='RFC5662' />).
    This includes both nfs types that end with a 4, such as
    offset4, length4, etc., as well as more generic types such as
    uint32_t and uint64_t.
  </t>

  <section anchor="code_copyright" title="Code Components Licensing Notice">
    <t>
      Both the XDR description and the scripts used for extracting
      the XDR description
      are Code Components as described in Section 4 of
      <xref target="LEGAL">"Legal Provisions Relating to IETF Documents"</xref>.
      These Code Components are licensed according to the terms of that
      document.
    </t>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <figure>
      <artwork>
/// /*
///  * Copyright (c) 2012 IETF Trust and the persons identified
///  * as authors of the code. All rights reserved.
///  *
///  * Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with
///  * or without modification, are permitted provided that the
///  * following conditions are met:
///  *
///  * o Redistributions of source code must retain the above
///  *   copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
///  *   following disclaimer.
///  *
///  * o Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
///  *   copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
///  *   following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
///  *   materials provided with the distribution.
///  *
///  * o Neither the name of Internet Society, IETF or IETF
///  *   Trust, nor the names of specific contributors, may be
///  *   used to endorse or promote products derived from this
///  *   software without specific prior written permission.
///  *
///  *   THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
///  *   AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
///  *   WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
///  *   IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
///  *   FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO
///  *   EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE
///  *   LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,
///  *   EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT
///  *   NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
///  *   SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS
///  *   INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
///  *   LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
///  *   OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
///  *   IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF
///  *   ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
///  *
///  * This code was derived from RFCTBD10.
///  * Please reproduce this note if possible.
///  */
///
/// /*
///  * flex_files_prot.x
///  */
///
/// /*
///  * The following include statements are for example only.
///  * The actual XDR definition files are generated separately
///  * and independently and are likely to have a different name.
///  * %#include &lt;nfsv42.x&gt;
///  * %#include &lt;rpc_prot.x&gt;
///  */
///
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
