<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2017) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2017) -->

<section title="Flexible File Layout Type v2" anchor="sec:flexLayout">
  <t>
    This document defines structures associated with the layouttype4
    value LAYOUT4_FLEX_FILES_V2 and it presents the minimal XDR
    changes neccessary from LAYOUT4_FLEX_FILES, which is described
    in <xref target="flexfiles" />.  <xref target="RFC5661" /> specifies
    the loc_body structure as an XDR type "opaque".  The opaque
    layout is uninterpreted by the generic pNFS client layers, but
    is interpreted by the flexible file layout type
    implementation.  This section defines the structure of this
    otherwise opaque value, ffv2_layout4.
  </t>

  <section title="ffv2_layout4" anchor="ffv2_layout4">

    <t>
      &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
    </t>

    <figure>
      <artwork>
/// struct ffv2_data_server4 {
///     deviceid4               ffds_deviceid;
///     uint32_t                ffds_efficiency;
///     stateid4                ffds_stateid&lt;&gt;;
///     nfs_fh4                 ffds_fh_vers&lt;&gt;;
///     fattr4_owner            ffds_user;
///     fattr4_owner_group      ffds_group;
///     opaque_auth             ffds_auth;
/// };
///
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <artwork>
/// struct ffv2_mirror4 {
///     ffv2_data_server4         ffm_data_servers&lt;&gt;;
/// };
///
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <artwork>
/// struct ffv2_layout4 {
///     length4                 ffl_stripe_unit;
///     ffv2_mirror4            ffl_mirrors&lt;&gt;;
///     ff_flags4               ffl_flags;
///     uint32_t                ffl_stats_collect_hint;
/// };
///
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <t>
      &lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
    </t>

    <t>
      The ffv2_layout4 structure specifies a layout over a set of
      mirrored copies of that portion of the data file described in
      the current layout segment.  
    </t>

    <t>
      It is possible that the file is concatenated from more than
      one layout segment.  Each layout segment MAY represent different
      striping parameters, applying respectively only to the layout
      segment byte range.
    </t>

    <t>
      The ffl_stripe_unit field is the stripe unit size in use for
      the current layout segment. The number of stripes is given
      inside each mirror by the number of elements in ffm_data_servers.
      If the number of stripes is one, then the value for ffl_stripe_unit
      MUST default to zero.  The only supported mapping scheme is
      sparse and is detailed in Section 6 of <xref target='flexfiles' />.
      Note that there is an assumption here that both the stripe
      unit size and the number of stripes is the same across all
      mirrors.
    </t>

    <t>
      The ffl_mirrors field is the array of mirrored storage devices
      which provide the storage for the current stripe, see 
      <xref target='fig:ff_layout' />.
    </t>

    <figure anchor="fig:ff_layout">
      <artwork>
                   +-----------+
                   |           |
                   |           |
                   |   File    |
                   |           |
                   |           |
                   +-----+-----+
                         |
            +------------+------------+
            |                         |
       +----+-----+             +-----+----+
       | Mirror 1 |             | Mirror 2 |
       +----+-----+             +-----+----+
            |                         |
       +-----------+            +-----------+
       |+-----------+           |+-----------+
       ||+-----------+          ||+-----------+
       +||  Storage  |          +||  Storage  |
        +|  Devices  |           +|  Devices  |
         +-----------+            +-----------+
      </artwork>
    </figure>

    <t>
      The ffs_mirrors field represents an array of state information
      for each mirrored copy of the current layout segment. Each
      element is described by a ffv2_mirror4 type.
    </t>

    <t>
      ffds_deviceid provides the deviceid of the storage device
      holding the data file.
    </t>

    <t>
      ffds_fh_vers is an array of filehandles of the data file
      matching to the available NFS versions on the given storage
      device.  There MUST be exactly as many elements in ffds_fh_vers
      as there are in both ffda_versions (see 4.1 of <xref target='flexfiles' />)
      and ffds_stateid. Each element of the array
      corresponds to a particular combination of ffdv_version,
      ffdv_minorversion, and ffdv_tightly_coupled provided
      for the device.  The array allows for server implementations
      which have different filehandles for different combinations of
      version, minor version, and coupling strength. See
      Section 5.3 of <xref target='flexfiles' /> for how to handle
      versioning issues between the client and storage devices.
    </t>

    <t>
      For tight coupling, ffds_stateid provides
      the stateids to be used by the client to access the file. For
      loose coupling and a NFSv4 storage device, the client may use
      anonymous stateids to perform I/O on the storage device as
      there is no use for the metadata server stateid (no control
      protocol). In such a scenario, the server MUST set the
      ffds_stateids to be anonymous stateids.
    </t>

    <t>
      For loose coupling, ffds_auth provides the RPC credentials needed
      for secure access to the storage devices. If secure access is
      not needed, i.e., the synthetic ids are sufficient, or in a tight
      coupling, the server should use the AUTH_NONE flavor and a zero
      length opaque body to minimize the returned structure length.
      As it may not be possible to invalidate the credential stashed
      in ffds_auth, the synthetic ids are still present in
      ffv2_data_server4 to allow the metadata server to fence off
      the client (see Section 2.2 of <xref target='flexfiles' />).
    </t>

    <t>
      As ffds_user, ffds_group, and ffds_auth are all controlled by
      the metadata server, there is no need for there to be
      exactly as many elements as in the ffds_fh_vers array.
      Note that each of the ffds_fh_vers, ffda_versions, and
      ffds_stateid are controlled by the storage device.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
