<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2017) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2017) -->

<section anchor="sec:security" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
    All of the security considerations to <xref target='flexfiles' />
    apply here. In addition, this document addresses how
    security mechanisms, such as Kerberos V5 GSS-API <xref target='RFC4121' />,
    can be applied to the loosely coupled model.
  </t>

  <section anchor="ss:security:krb5" title="RPCSEC_GSS and Security Services">
    <section anchor="ss:sec:krb5:lc" title="Loosely Coupled">
      <t>
        The combination of the metadata server and the storage devices
        consitute a storage cluster, or more simply, cluster.
        If an implementation chooses to employ RPCSEC_GSSv3 via an
        RPC-application-defined structured privilege assertion in a
        manner described in Section 4.9.1 of <xref target='RFC7862' />,
        then a single security realm is used by the clustered system.
        If however the implementation utilizes ffds_auth to transfer
        security credentials, then two security realms are used
        by the cluster:

        <list style='format (%d)'>
          <t>
            Organizational - the RPC credentials used for a client
            to authenticate to the metadata server are generated
            by an external security server. The metadata server
            has no special priveleges with this server.
          </t>

          <t>
            Cluster - the RPC credentials used for a client to
            authenticate to the storage device are generated by
            a security server internal to the cluster. The metadata
            server has special priveleges with this server.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Inside the cluster realm, the storage devices are considered
        an extension of the metadata server.  This may mean that under
        a Kerberos V5 GSS-API <xref target='RFC4121' /> based system,
        the metadata server has a copy of the private key for the
        storage device. Also, the special privelge could mean one or
        more of the metadata server beinbg colocated with the
        Kerberos Domain Controller (KDC) (AI: check), the metadata server has
        access to the KDC database, or the metadata server is allowed
        by the KDC to use S4U2Proxy. (AI: cite)
      </t>

      <t>
        Such "credentials" should be limited to just the data file
        be accessed.  Using Kerberos V5 GSS-API <xref target='RFC4121' />,
        some possible approaches would be:

        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            a dedicated/throwaway client principal name akin to the
            synthetic uid/gid schemes.
          </t>

          <t>
            authorization data in the ticket.
          </t>

          <t>
            an out-of-band scheme between the client and metadata server.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Depending on the implementation details, fencing would then be
        controlled either by expiring the credential or by modifying
        the synthetic uid or gid on the data file. I.e., if the
        credentials are at a finer granularity than the synthetic
        ids, it might be possible to also fence just one client from
        the file.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
