<!-- Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2017) -->
<!-- Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2017) -->

<section anchor="sec:intro" title="Introduction">
  <t>
    In the parallel Network File System (pNFS), the metadata server
    returns layout type structures that describe where file data
    is located.  There are different layout types for different
    storage systems and methods of arranging data on storage devices.
    <xref target="flexfiles" /> defines the flexible file layout type used with
    file-based data servers that are accessed using the Network File
    System (NFS) protocols: NFSv3 <xref target="RFC1813" />, NFSv4.0 <xref
    target="RFC7530" />, NFSv4.1 <xref target="RFC5661" />, and NFSv4.2
    <xref target="RFC7862" />.
  </t>

  <t>
    The first version of the flexible file layout type had two issues
    which could not be addressed in <xref target="flexfiles" /> because
    of existing implementations. The first issue was that under
    the tightly coupled model for a NFSv4 implementation, either
    a global stateid or an anonymous stateid needed to be used. The
    second issue was that under the loosely coupled model, for
    a secure Remote Procedural Call (RPC) (<xref target='RFC5531' />) implementation,
    each of the client, metadata server, and storage devices needed to
    implement an RPC-application-defined structured privilege assertion
    with RPCSEC_GSS version 3 (RPCSEC_GSSv3) <xref target='RFC7861' />.
    The second version of the flexible file layout type addresses
    both of these issues.
  </t>

  <section anchor='sec:defs' title='Definitions'>
    <t>
      <list style='hanging'>
        <t hangText='control communication requirements:'>
          defines for a layout type the details regarding
          information on layouts, stateids, file metadata, and file
          data which must be  communicated between the metadata
          server and the storage devices.
        </t>

        <t hangText='control protocol:'>
          defines a particular mechanism that an implementation of a
          layout type would use to meet the control communication
          requirement for that layout type.  This need not be a
          protocol as normally understood.  In some cases the same
          protocol may be used as a control protocol and data access
          protocol.
        </t>

        <t hangText='data file:'>
          is that part of the file system object which contains
          the content.
        </t>

        <t hangText='fencing:'>
          is when the metadata server prevents the storage devices
          from processing I/O from a specific client to a specific
          file.
        </t>

        <t hangText='file layout type:'>
          is a layout type in which the storage devices
          are accessed via the NFS protocol (see Section 13
          of <xref target='RFC5661' />).
        </t>

        <t hangText='layout:'>
          informs a client of which storage devices it needs to
          communicate with (and over which protocol) to perform I/O
          on a file. The layout might also provide some hints about
          how the storage is physically organized.
        </t>

        <t hangText='layout iomode:'>
          describes whether the layout granted to the client is for
          read or read/write I/O.
        </t>

        <t hangText='layout stateid:'>
          is a 128-bit quantity returned by a server that
          uniquely defines the layout state provided by the server
          for a specific layout that describes a layout type and
          file (see Section 12.5.2 of <xref target='RFC5661' />).
          Further, Section 12.5.3 of <xref target='RFC5661' />
          describes the difference between
          a layout stateid and a normal stateid.
        </t>

        <t hangText='layout type:'>
          describes both the storage protocol used to
          access the data and the aggregation scheme used to lay out
          the file data on the underlying storage devices.
        </t>

        <t hangText='loose coupling:'>
          is when the metadata server and the storage devices
          do not have a control protocol present.
        </t>

        <t hangText='metadata file:'>
          is that part of the file system object which describes
          the object and not the content. E.g., it could be the
          time since last modification, access, etc.
        </t>

        <t hangText='metadata server (MDS):'>
          is the pNFS server which provides metadata information
          for a file system object. It also is responsible for
          generating layouts for file system objects. Note that
          the MDS is responsible for directory-based operations.
        </t>

        <t hangText='recalling a layout:'>
          is when the metadata server uses a back channel to inform
          the client that the layout is to be returned in a graceful
          manner. Note that the client has the opportunity to flush any
          writes, etc., before replying to the metadata server.
        </t>

        <t hangText='revoking a layout:'>
          is when the metadata server invalidates the layout such
          that neither the metadata server nor any storage device
          will accept any access from the client with that layout.
        </t>

        <t hangText='stateid:'>
          is a 128-bit quantity returned by a server that uniquely
          defines the open and locking states provided by the server
          for a specific open-owner or lock-owner/open-owner pair
          for a specific file and type of lock.
        </t>

        <t hangText='storage device:'>
          designates the target to which clients may direct I/O requests
          when they hold an appropriate layout.  See Section 2.1 of
          <xref target='pNFSLayouts' /> for further discussion of
          the difference between a data store and a storage device.
        </t>

        <t hangText='tight coupling:'>
          is when the metadata server and the storage devices
          do have a control protocol present.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Language">
    <t>
      The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
      &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
      &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
      &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
      interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
